Welcome to the Genmab Website Design System Designer tutorial.
This video is for designers creating website experiences for Genmab.
Use of the design system is a required part of the website
design process for all agency partners.
In this video, we'll walk through how to access the design
system, understand and leverage its various features,
how to move from design to development, plus where to go for support.
To get the latest version of the website design kit.
Go to helix and navigate to Channel Guidance,
then websites.
Website design system,
website design kit
and finally design Kit.
Click the button to open the file in view only mode.
From there, use the dropdown menu to duplicate it to your drafts.
This creates a new file with all permissions removed
so you can edit, rename, save, and move it wherever you like.
Finally, to make sure you have the latest version, click this button.
It will link to the current file or newer version if one is available.
Now that you have created your own
copy of the design kit file, let's take a look at what's inside.
Starting with the left sidebar, the Pages and Layers panel,
we have the Getting Started page,
which contains an overview of the content along with direct
links to specific pages within the kit.
Next is the foundations page covering design, kit, essentials, color
and theme modes, typography and columns.
The presets page contains desktop, tablet and mobile page frames
based on website type, with navigation and theme modes already applied.
The component overview page provides an at a glance listing
of all components, with links to the component reference pages.
The next set of pages cover each component in detail,
including properties and variants, as well as color and font options.
And finally, the changelog page lists version and update details.
Moving over to the right sidebar, the Properties and Inspector panel
you will find available text styles, effects and layout guides.
Theme modes included in this version of the design
kit can be viewed in the variables panel.
Keep in mind that the right sidebar is contextual
and will change depending on what is selected on the canvas.
The first step in creating
a website is choosing a preset based on website type.
There are three preset types. Brand.
Brand with indication selector and Genmab Corporate.
This version of the design kit also includes a MyNavCare preset.
Each preset includes desktop,
tablet, and mobile page frames with an applied
theme mode along with header, footer, and navigation flows.
There are two sub navigation options to choose from.
A full width menu and dropdown menu.
The page frames also have Auto Layout applied
to support drag and drop page creation.
For this tutorial, we will use the BrandMab preset.
Once you have selected a preset, it's
time to think about file structure
and where the website design will live.
As you become familiar with the kit and components,
you'll find the workflow that works best for you.
In this tutorial,
we'll share some preferred methods
for structuring the file and adding components.
Keep in mind,
unless the kit is published
within your organization as a design library,
the website design will need to remain
in this file to access components locally.
Let's begin by renaming the design kit.
A clean version of
the original design kit can be used for the next project,
or related deliverables can be added to this file.
Now let's copy and paste the preset to a new page
and give it a name.
Move the pages from the preset
frame onto the canvas and rename.
For the navigation.
Create a separate frame showing all expanded views.
Now we're ready to start adding components.
Adding components to
the page is simple and can be done in a couple of ways.
Starting with the desktop page, let's add a hero.
We can drag the component directly from the assets panel onto the page.
Positioning the cursor
where we would like it to appear in the stacking order.
Or we can select a component
already in the page frame and use the swap instance function.
Duplicating components within the auto layout frame
and using swap instance is one of the fastest ways to add components.
while designing the page.
If we configure the desktop component first
with the desired variant properties and content,
we can then use copy and paste to replace
across the tablet and mobile pages.
Update the device variants and only configure the component once.
Reducing errors and speeding up development.
Finally, it's worth mentioning that
because all components
are designed at desktop, tablet, and mobile widths,
keeping the page frame auto layout set to top center
with horizontal and vertical hug enabled is recommended.
Now that we've added components to the page, let's take a closer
look at how they work.
The component library
consists of two main types based components—
Single reusable elements like buttons, containers, and text,
and component groups
or patterns such as navigation bars, hero sections, and card layouts.
Components are listed
alphabetically in the Assets Panel,
and can be viewed in either grid or list view.
Make sure show subfolders is selected.
This keeps component atoms
grouped inside folders and out of the way for easier browsing.
When designing a website, we should always use instances
of these pre-built patterns
and configure them
using the available variants, properties and color options.
Detaching components is not recommended or supported,
except in a few cases covered later in the tutorial.
Keeping components connected is important
because detached instances no longer receive updates
or have access to component properties and variants.
Connected components help maintain
consistency, reduce errors, and speeds up development.
Finally, while this design system does
support atomic design through custom
layouts built with base components, it should be used sparingly
since it requires more time for both design and development.
Variants and properties make components more flexible
and reusable while maintaining consistency across the design system.
An easy way to explore component
variants and properties is in the details panel.
Let's take a look at the hero component.
Variants are different versions of a component grouped
within the same component set.
They allow you to switch between options such as device type, style,
image position, and more without creating separate components.
Properties are customizable settings within a component that allow you
to change content,
behavior, or visibility without detaching the component.
Nested properties
become available
when a base component is placed inside a larger component,
such as a button inside a hero.
You can also preview the different theme modes.
The design kit also includes a reference page for each component,
showing the available variants, properties, and color options.
The main component is included for publishing purposes only
and should never be edited.
All components have default
color and font styles applied as defined by the theme modes.
Additional options can be applied to an instance using the Properties
and Inspector panel.
Let's take a look at the color bar card component and see how.
The first step is to go to the component reference page.
Apply the mode you're working in and review the available options.
BrandMab is the default theme mode for this version of the design kit.
Here you can see the available options six background colors,
six bar colors, and the ability to change the font size and style
To apply a different color,
select the instance Open Selection colors and choose a new color
that corresponds to the color variable you want to change.
To change a font size or style,
select the text layer and apply the new size and or style.
Headline sizes are specific to desktop, tablet, and mobile.
While body sizes are shared across all three.
To add an effect such as the container drop shadow,
select a container instance and choose the effects style.
Keep in mind that color options and font customization
vary by component, so be sure to check the reference pages before
making any changes.
Let's take a look at how images work within the design system.
Images exist both as base components and as nested components
within larger patterns like heros, content blocks and cards.
The base component settings default to square corners,
image position top center, and captions turned on.
Placeholder graphics are included that can be used for wireframing,
deleted or left hidden in the instance.
For now, let's turn off the caption.
Corners,
which are defined by the active theme mode
can be set to square or radius.
Image position defines how the image crops
as the viewport gets smaller and components become narrower.
Always choose the image position
variant before applying the image fill.
Image position top center works best for centered
focal points, cropping the left and right sides equally.
To accurately represent this in your design.
Select the image layer, apply an image fill and set it to fill.
This automatically positions
the image and only needs to be done once in the desktop variant.
Image positions top left and top right,
Pin the image to one side as the viewport narrows.
Cropping only one side of the image
to accurately represent this in your design.
Select the image layer, apply an image fill, set it to fill,
then switch to crop and manually reposition
the image by sliding it left or right.
This will need to be done for desktop, tablet and mobile.
An additional image fill option can be found in components
with background image variants.
This Gradient Overlay
option helps maintain contrast and improves text readability.
You can adjust the number of stops, direction, colors, and opacity.
Gradient overlays are added by the builder using standard CSS gradients
and should not be included in the exported image.
Also, for these variants, the image position
will need to be manually annotated in the file.
Finally, images can be exported directly from Figma
or an image editing application.
Both methods
require specific sizing and cropping approaches
depending on the image position you've selected.
As a general rule, size your image to match the height
and width of the desktop image at 2x resolution.
We recommend using the WebP file format.
SVG images are recommended for vector graphics.
Note that the hero component requires
a mobile specific crop and export.